Guide to the Rob Amberg photographs and papers, 1975-2009 and undated RL.00031
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rob Amberg photographs and papers
1975-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Amberg, Rob
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.00031
15 Linear Feet
The photographs and papers of documentarian Rob Amberg span the years 1975-2009. The gelatin silver prints and pigmented inkjet color prints in the collection represent three bodies of work: The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress; The Sodom Laurel Album; and The Vanishing Culture of Agriculture. Amberg focuses primarily on the social life and customs of the rural South, especially in the mountains of his home state of North Carolina. Images range from landscape shots taken before and during construction of an interstate highway in the N.C. mountains, to portraits of individuals and families affected by the changes in rural culture. Images also depict agricultural activies such as tobacco cultivation and dairy cattle farming, as well as work in the poultry industry. He has a special concern for documenting the way in which industrial and economic progress seems to be erasing many aspects of rural culture at the turn of the twenty-first century. Amberg's papers account for the rest of the collection and are organized into five series: Correspondence, Printed Materials, Subject Files, and Writings and Research, and Audio. Acquired as part of the Archives of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
457 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rob Amberg Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2004, 2007, and 2008. The Papers were received in 2011.
Biographical Note
Rob Amberg's photographs and writings have been exhibited and published nationally and internationally in journals, magazines, and galleries. He lectures frequently and performs regular documentary assignments for non-profit organizations, philanthropic foundations and editorial publications. He is the recipient of fellowships and awards from numerous organizations, including: the National Endowment for the Humanities, the John Simon Guggenheim Foundation, the Center for Documentary Studies, Alternate Roots, the North Carolina Humanities Council, and the National Endowment for the Arts.
His book, Sodom Laurel Album, was published in 2002 by the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University and the University of North Carolina Press. The book received the 2003 Thomas Wolfe Memorial Literary Award from the Western North Carolina Historical Association. In 2005, his work was included in the book Quartet: Four North Carolina Photographers, which was published by Safe Harbor Books. His latest book, The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress, was published in 2009 by the Center for American Places and the University of Georgia Press.
Collection Overview
The Rob Amberg Photographs and Papers span the years 1975-2009. The photographs consist of 8x10 and 11x14 inch gelatin silver prints and pigmented inkjet color prints. Amberg's focus as a photographer is primarily the social customs of the rural South, especially in his home state of North Carolina. He has a special concern for documenting the way in which industrial and economic progress seems to be erasing many aspects of rural culture at the turn of the twenty-first century.
The collection is arranged into three project series: The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress; The Sodom Laurel Album; and The Vanishing Culture of Agriculture.
Images range from landscape shots taken before and during construction of an interstate highway in the N.C. mountains, to portraits of individuals and families affected by the changes in rural culture. Images also depict agricultural activies such as tobacco cultivation and dairy cattle farming, as well as work in the poultry industry. Many of Amberg's images in this last series were funded by the Rural Advancement Fund to document the rural Carolinas, and by the Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation. Captions and numbering are taken from original notes on the back of each print. Series are arranged in alphabetical order by title of project.
Amberg's papers are organized into five series. The Correspondence Series contains incoming messages regarding exhibits and the publication of Amberg's books as well as photographic work in other published materials.
The Printed Material Series consists of publications which include or feature his images. Publications in the series are both national and local, including The New York Times and Harper's.
Amberg worked and contributed to a number of non-profit organizations dealing with farm worker's rights and other social issues. Collections of materials relating to these non-profits are housed in the Subject Files Series. Printed materials in this series include annual reports and publications by each organization. Most of the materials include photography work by Amberg.
Included in Amberg's papers is the Writings and Research Series. Content includes multiple versions of the manuscripts to The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress and Sodom Laurel Album, a publisher's draft of Quartet: Four North Carolina Photographers, a number of interview transcripts, and other writings by Amberg and others.
The final grouping in the collection is the Audio Series which includes a piece entitled Interstate 26 produced by Leda Hartman and a copy of the musical recording which accompanies Sodom Laurel Album.
Related Material
Selected images from the Rob Amberg Photographs are featured on the Duke University Libraries Digital Collections website. The original library exhibit, displayed in 2009, was entitled The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress.
Interstate 26 -- Pictorial works; Interstate highway system -- North Carolina -- History; Documentary photographers -- United States; Documentary Photography -- North Carolina -- Madison County; Southern States -- Social conditions; Progress -- Psychological aspects; Roads -- North Carolina -- Design and construction; Landscape changes -- Psychological aspects; Land use -- Southern States; Tobacco farmers -- North Carolina -- Madison County -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Tobacco farmers -- North Carolina -- Madison County; Poultry industry -- North Carolina -- Pictorial works; North Carolina -- Photographs; Country life -- North Carolina -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Dairy farming -- Southern States -- Pictorial works; Tobacco -- North Carolina; Agriculture -- Southern States; Inkjet prints; Color photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Amberg, Rob -- Sodom Laurel Album; Amberg, Rob; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress, 1978-2004, 8 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of 127 photographs, the majority of which are 11x14 inch gelatin silver prints, although there is a small series of digital color prints. Through images of landscapes, individuals, and communities, the photographs provide an intimate, long-term look at the social, cultural, and environmental impact of the construction of an interstate highway through rural Madison County, North Carolina. The series is divided into three subseries: Color Prints, Exhibit Prints (from Duke University's Special Collections Gallery exhibit in 2009), and Loose Prints (not included in the 2009 exhibit). Original captions and numbering taken from back of prints. Subseries arranged alphabetically.
  - Color Prints, 2006-2007
    Consists of 15 unmatted 8.5x11 inch color prints detailing not only I-26, but also the development of Wolf Ridge Resort in Madison County, North Carolina. Color prints made on an Epson 2400 inkjet printer with Epson Ultra Premium Photo Paper and Epson pigmented inks.
    - Driving with Kate through the Low Gap on the Old Mountain Road, Lower Paw Paw, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_0439)
    - At the junction of Lower Paw Paw Road and Little Pine Road at Kalamazoo, Little Pine, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_5686)
    - New gated driveway, Laurel River Road, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2006 (Box 1, Image IMG_4278)
    - The Laurel River Bridge, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_4312)
    - Jasper Jenkins with his daughter Cleta Willis and her husband Bobby Willis, at the Family Cemetery Plot, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_3579)
    - Overlook sign at the new Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_9455)
    - Local signage at Exit 3 on I-26, Bear Branch, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_3098)
    - Artists rendering of the entrance to the Wolf Ridge Resort, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_6037)
    - New condominiums at the Wolf Ridge Resort, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_9134)
    - New swimming pool at Wolf Ridge Resort, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_9108)
    - Garland Galloway, Founder of Laurel Valley Watch, speaking to the Madison County Planning and Zoning Board about the effects of Wolf Ridge Resort on the community, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2006 (Box 1, Image IMG_6741)
    - Katie Caskey toasting her parents at their 25th anniversary party at the Arts Sanctuary in downtown Marshall, Madison County, N.C., 2006 (Box 1, Image IMG_5980)
    - Opening reception at Marshall High Studios, Marshall, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_4371)
    - At the Madison Celebrates Art Festival, Marshall, Madison County, N.C., 2006 (Box 1, Image IMG_5736)
    - Picnic on Blanahassett Island, Marshall, Madison County, N.C., 2007 (Box 1, Image IMG_9145)
  - Exhibit Prints, 1994-2004
    Consists of 45 11x14 inch silver gelatin prints, four of which are loose, and 41 which are in 16x20 inch mats. The four loose prints were scanned and hung in the exhibit as 3x4 foot images. The prints in this subseries were exhibited at Duke University's Special Collections Gallery from January 12 through March 29, 2009 and are available on the Duke University Libraries Digital Collections website under the title of the original exhibit, "The New Road: I-26 and the Footprints of Progress."
    - (Unmatted print) Cleared hillside, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 2, Image #98084-d36)
    - (Unmatted print) Supervisors inspecting site of recent blast, Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 2, Image #970026-3)
    - (Unmatted print) Howard and Lucille Babbitt picking apples from their orchard for the last time, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 2, Image #950136-17)
    - (Unmatted print) Vault being exhumed from Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 2, Image #960122-16)
    - (Matted print) J.D. Thomas walking away from his burning home place, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 3, Image #970057-g35)
    - (Matted print) Interior of the Little Creek Cafe, founded by Edna Boone in 1951, US-23 and Laurel River Road, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 3, Image #950077-4)
    - (Matted print) Memorial wreath on US-23, Murray Mountain, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 3, Image #970129-20)
    - (Matted print) North Carolina Department of Transportation boundary marker, near the Appalachian Trail at Sam's Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 3, Image #960074-17)
    - (Matted print) Looking at I-26 and the visitor center from Dale and Lurethra Fluty's front yard, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 3, Image #03017-3)
    - (Matted print) Manufactured home on the I-26 corridor with Buckner Gap and the Fluty Farm in the background, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2004 (Box 3, Image #04004-34)
    - (Matted print) Real estate office, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 3, Image #02036-16)
    - (Matted print) Herbalist Lisa Ganora, who sometimes goes by the name White Wolf, searching for plants to rescue on the proposed right-of-way for I-26, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 4, Image #970055-16)
    - (Matted print) Aerial boundary marker in the woods indicating the I-26 right-of-way, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 4, Image #98040-22)
    - (Matted print) I-beams on the Laurel River Bridge, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2001 (Box 4, Image #01009-33)
    - (Matted print) Harold Wallin in the pasture above his house, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 4, Image #970064-36)
    - (Matted print) US-23 North, near Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 4, Image #03062-15)
    - (Matted print) Water plants, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 4, Image #960073-29)
    - (Matted print) Poplar tree, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 4, Image #970130-24)
    - (Matted print) North Carolina Department of Transportation Geologist Rick Lockamy identifying points on the map to take core rock samples, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1994 (Box 5, Image #940153-36)
    - (Matted print) At Mile Marker 6 on the evening before the I-26 dedication, I-26, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 5, Image #03092-f35)
    - (Matted print) Headstones and footstones from the Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 5, Image #960123-18)
    - (Matted print) Spraying concrete with water to keep it from curing too fast, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2001 (Box 5, Image #01004-26)
    - (Matted print) Appalachian Quilt Shop, US-23 North, near Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 5, Image #950076-32)
    - (Matted print) Culvert pipe and barn, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 5, Image #99025-5)
    - (Matted print) Sam Gray carrying a chestnut stump from the woods, Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 5, Image #95001-43)
    - (Matted print) Stone glyph built by Iktome, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 6, Image #99038-34)
    - (Matted print) Iktome glyph and 190-ton dump trucks, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 6, Image #98115-28)
    - (Matted print) Workers washing the "Welcome to Madison County" sign, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 6, Image #03099-34)
    - (Matted print) Drill lines on the face of the 600 foot cut at Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 6, Image #00055-19)
    - (Matted print) Paving near California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 6, Image #02042-3)
    - (Matted print) Bridge abutments and barn, Higgins Branch, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 6, Image #98082-12)
    - (Matted print) North Carolina Department of Transportation right-of-way flag indicating the centerline of the proposed I-26, Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 6, Image #970132-29)
    - (Matted print) Benched hillside, California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 7, Image #98112-1)
    - (Matted print) Grapevine, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 7, Image #970130-14)
    - (Matted print) Checking asphalt density, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 7, Image #03085-3)
    - (Matted print) Aerial seeding for erosion control, Jarvis Branch, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 7, Image #03035-16)
    - (Matted print) Praying over graves at New Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 7, Image #960128-19)
    - (Matted print) Power shovel clearing land in preparation for burning, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 7, Image #00065-24)
    - (Matted print) Unidentified infant graves at Woody Family Cemetery, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 7, Image #960131-5)
    - (Matted print) Homemade sign over the Little Ivy Church Cemetery during grave removal, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 8, Image #960123-28)
    - (Matted print) Reburial at the New Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 8, Image #960121-6)
    - (Matted print) Pan shaping mountain to grade level, Bear Branch, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 8, Image #98079-21)
    - (Matted print) Trees being removed and burned, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 8, Image #00053-25)
    - (Matted print) Stone glyph built by Iktome, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 8, Image #98077-8)
    - (Matted print) Unidentified grave at the New Higgins Branch Cemetery, Higgins Branch, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 8, Image #02036-2)
  - Loose Prints, 1978-2004
    Consists of 67 unmatted 11x14 black and white prints which also document the I-26 construction through Madison County, North Carolina. These were not included in the Duke University 2009 exhibit.
    - Creating grooves on the highway's shoulders, California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 9, Image #02055-15)
    - Paving supervisors checking blueprints, near California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 9, Image #02043-3)
    - Near Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2002 (Box 9, Image #02042-15)
    - Erosion control matting, near Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 9, Image #98078-13)
    - False wall built around abutment at Laurel River Bridge, Laurel River Road, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 9, Image #99041-25)
    - The New Laurel River Bridge, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 9, Image #00154-18)
    - Erosion control matting and rip rap, US-23, near Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 9, Image #99026-34)
    - Spraying to remove loose rock from the exposed face of the mountain, Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 9, Image #00056-27)
    - Man spreading mulch at the Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03025-34)
    - I-26 at Exit 11, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03022-11)
    - Dignitaries podium at the I-26 Dedication, I-26 Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03105-5)
    - VIP seating at the I-26 Dedication, Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03100-14)
    - Veterans of Foreign Wars Honor Guard at the I-26 Dedication, Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03100-13)
    - Veterans of Foreign Wars Trumpeter at the I-26 Dedication, Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03102-4)
    - Governor Mike Easley greeting at the I-26 Dedication, Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 9, Image #03106-34)
    - The new Waffle House, Highway 213, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 2004 (Box 9, Image #04001-17)
    - Looking north at I-26 from the Highway 213 Bridge, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 9, Image #98045-17)
    - Looking southeast from the westbound overlook, I-26, near California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 10, Image #03022-3)
    - Simon Peter Norton, Jr. at the new I-26 Visitors Center, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 10, Image #03060-25)
    - Dellie Norton's work shed, Sodom Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 1978 (Box 10, Image #78083-8)
    - Mile Marker and spring-fed fountain, US-23 at Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2004 (Box 10, Image #04011-30)
    - Tobacco barn, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 10, Image #97088-3)
    - Sign on NC-212, Shelton Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 10, Image #98083-9)
    - Appalachian Trail hikers preparing to cross US-23, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 10, Image #03034-5)
    - Iktome glyphs and symbols, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 10, Image #99022-2)
    - Iktome glyph, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 10, Image #98077-33)
    - Herbalist Lisa Ganora digging a white trillium for transplanting to her home garden, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 10, Image #970069-28)
    - Jenkins Nursery, US-23 North, Sams Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 10, Image #950075-34)
    - Steve and Audrey Snyder and their daughters and pet goat, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 10, Image #970065-7)
    - Iktome walking on I-26 right-of-way near his home, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 10, Image #98120-29)
    - Ribbon-cutting at the dedication of the Tennessee portion of I-26, near Sams Gap, Unicoi County, Tenn., 1995 (Box 10, Image #950057-26)
    - Miss Unicoi County at the dedication of the Tennessee portion of I-26, near Sams Gap, Unicoi County, Tenn., 1995 (Box 10, Image #950056-11)
    - Billie Lundford in her store, US-23 North, Bear Branch, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 10, Image #960133-28a)
    - Chris Carter moving his home from the I-26 right-of-way, Higgins Branch, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 10, Image #960132-25)
    - Mr. and Mrs. May at their home on the I-26 right-of-way, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960255-25)
    - At the Wolf Laurel Road and US-23, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 11, Image #03067-31)
    - At the junction of Wolf Laurel Road and US-23 North, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 11, Image #03062-6)
    - Clifford Woody's barn and tobacco patch, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1999 (Box 11, Image #99027-D36)
    - Clate Grindstatt's house which was destroyed by an out of control truck, US-23, Murray Mountain, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 11, Image #970129-3)
    - Charles Carter and Kenneth Buckner preparing to bury Carter's mule, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 11, Image #97025-14)
    - Community Announcements Board, Wolf Laurel Road and US-23, Upper Laurel, Madison County, N.C., 2003 (Box 11, Image #03067-24)
    - Springbox still holding water, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 11, Image #98046-27)
    - Device measuring sedimentation levels, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 11, Image #98060-5)
    - Identifying graves at the New Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960121-32)
    - North Carolina Department of Transportation inspector removing a king snake from the former site of the Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960185-18)
    - Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960011-13)
    - Mrs. Delzia Rasmussen standing between the graves of her husband and her mother at Little Ivy Church Cemetery, Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960010-24)
    - Grave digger probing ground for unmarked grave at Woody Family Cemetery, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 11, Image #960118-32)
    - Roadside stand, US-23 North, near Mars Hill, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 11, Image #98074-17)
    - Drill rig, Sprinkle Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1997 (Box 11, Image #970075-2)
    - Culvert pipe and drain pool, Bear Branch, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 11, Image #98047-20)
    - Scraped fill area, California Creek, Madison County, N.C., 1998 (Box 12, Image #98075-25)
    - Water filtration pond, Little Creek, Madison County, N.C., 2000 (Box 12, Image #00053-33)
    - Logging road, Buckner Gap, Madison County, N.C., 1995 (Box 12, Image #950010-43)
    - Ethel Rice checking the mail for her neighbor, Miss Zelda English, Laurel River Road, Madison County, N.C., 1996 (Box 12, Image #960191-10)
    - Penland and Sons Store, Marshall, Madison County, N.C., 1988 (Box 12, Image #88067-20)